RUIHAO LI

+1(216) 356-9082 \diamond Cleveland, OH

rxl527@case.edu \(\rightarrow \text{LinkedIn} \(\rightarrow \text{Personal Website} \(\rightarrow \text{GitHub} \)

PROFILE

Physics PhD candidate with research experience in topological quantum materials and quantum computing. Proficient in scientific programming tools such as Python, Julia, Mathematica, etc. Familiar with quantum development frameworks including Qiskit, PennyLane, and Braket. I am a Qiskit Advocate recognized by IBM.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Physics, Case Western Reserve University, USA

Expected 2023

Theoretical Condensed Matter Physics (Advisor: Shulei Zhang)

B.Sc. Honours (Advanced), The University of Sydney, Australia

Mar 2013 - Nov 2016

First Class Honours in Theoretical Particle Physics (Advisor: Michael A. Schmidt)

UCEAP exchange program, University of California San Diego, USA

Sept 2014 - Mar 2015

EXPERIENCE

QOSF Mentorship Program Mentee

Apr 2022 - Present

Quantum Open Source Foundation

Remote

- Conducted extensive literature review of the quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) under supervision of Kostas Blekos (University of Patras, Greece).
- Developed codebase based on *Qiskit* for benchmarking different QAOA variants (recursive-QAOA, warm-start-QAOA, QAOA+, etc.) on IBM quantum computers.
- Writing a review paper that aims to provide current status of and guidance for the QAOA (to appear on arXiv soon).

Qiskit Advocate Mentorship Program Mentee

Sept 2022 - Dec 2022

Qiskit - IBM Quantum

Remote

- Contributed to Qiskit-QEC, an open-source framework for quantum error correction, by implementing the XP stabilizer formalism under the supervision of Drew Vandeth and Grace Harper (IBM).
- Implemented XP operator algebra, modular arithmetics on $\mathbb{Z}/n\mathbb{Z}$ and functionality related to the Howell matrix transformation. Developed unittests for the codes.

Quantum Algorithms Research Intern

May 2022 - Aug 2022

Toronto, Canada

Aqnostiq

- Conducted research project on non-trivial variational quantum algorithms for anomaly/novelty detection.
- Developed and maintained codes based on *PennyLane* and *PyTorch* for numerical experiments of the project.
- Produced three tutorials on Machine Learning (hybrid computation, autoencoders, and quantum kernel training) for Covalent, a workflow orchestration tool that the company is actively developing.

RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

My current research encompasses two areas: 1. novel transport phenomena in topological semimetals; 2. quantum simulation of condensed matter systems. I have also worked on dark matter and neutrinos models in new gauge theories beyond the Standard Model. Publications can be found on my Google Scholar profile.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages Python, Julia, Mathematica, MATLAB, JavaScript, CSS, LaTeX, Bash

Toolkits NumPy, SciPy, Qiskit, PennyLane, Braket, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Scikit-learn, Covalent, Git, Slurm

LEADERSHIP

Qiskit Fall Fest 2022 Organizer, CWRU

Oct 2022

• Co-organized Qiskit Fall Fest 2022 at CWRU, where we hosted a week of quantum computing workshop series and a hackathon for students to take part in. Delivered a lecture on (Qiskit) quantum machine learning.

Condensed Matter Journal Club Organizer, CWRU

Jan 2022 - Apr 2022

• Co-organized the condensed matter journal club in Department of Physics, which brought in students from different research groups to present and discuss recent research progress in condensed matter physics.